A Guide to the Ella Katherine Fife Papers and Related Fife Family Correspondence, 1918 August 1-1919 February 21
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Ella Katherine Fife Papers and Related Fife Family Correspondence, 1918 August 1-1919 February 21
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5943-e
This collection consists of ca. 100 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift in honor of Ella Katherine Fife on her 100th birthday anniversary, 1986 December 17, by her daughter, Anne Eugenie Herndon Freudenberg.
Biographical/Historical Information
Ella Katherine Fife, R. N., University of Virginia Nursing School, Class of 1912, was attached to Base Hospital #41 sent from the University of Virginia and quartered at the School of Members of the Legion of Honor in St. Denis, outside Paris, adjoining the famous basilica there. Her brother, Col. James Douglas Fife, a career officer in the Medical Corps and graduate of the University of Virginia School of Medicine, Class of 1897, was in charge of procuring hospital quarters for the American and British forces in France. Ella Katherine Fife contracted influenza at St. Denis and after the Armistice was sent to Cannes to recuperate. Following the war she married Erhart Richard Freudenberg.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consists of ca. 100 items, 1975 November 5-1919 March 13. They contain the correspondence of Ella Katherine Fife, U. S. Army Nurse Corps, Base Hospital #41, American Expeditionary Force, consisting of 31 letters, 1918 August 1-1919 February 21, written by her, chiefly from St. Denis, France to her parents (Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife and Robert Herndon Fife, I, of "Oak Lawn") and to her siblings in Charlottesville.
The papers also contain 16 letters, 1918 February 2-1919 February 8, written to her by her brother, Col. James Douglas Fife, M.D., U. S. Army Medical Corps, Headquarters S. O. S., AEF, in France. The remaining letters from and between her parents and siblings, including the period when she was stationed at Camp Lee, Virginia. There are also 2 letters, 1918 December 5 and 29, from a friend, Nellie Nash, U. S. Naval Forces, Leith, Scotland, to Mrs. R. H. Fife; and 3 pictures [1916] from Camp Lee.
Key to Correspondents
Fife, Ella Katherine [17 December 1886 - 3 Jan, 1975] ("Ella" or "Nell" or "Nellie")
Fife, Sarah Ann Graves Strickler [Mrs. Robert Herndon Fife](Mother)
Fife, Robert Herndon I (Father)
Fife, James Douglas ("Jamie") (m. Katherine Mae Reynolds) (Brother) [son Robert Herndon Fife, III]
Fife, Margaret Whitler ("Madge") [later Mrs. William Crump Tucker of Richmond] (Sister)
Fife, William Ormond ("Will" or "Willie") (Brother)
Fife, Robert Herndon II ("Rob" or "Robbie")(Brother)
Rinehart, Mary Graves Fife ("Daisy") [Mrs. Charles Rinehart] (Sister)
Fife, Sleton Strickler [m. Mildred Irving Hill of Richmond] (Brother)
Fife, Katherine Mae Reynolds [Mrs. James Douglas Fife]
Nash, Nellie [friend]
Stricker, Hinda (sister of Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife)
Strickler, Ormond (brother of Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife)
Contents List
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 November 5, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 November 27, APCS
- J. Craig Anderson to Robert Herndon Fife, I and Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife ante 1917 December 6, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 December 6, ALS
- Shelton Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 December 12, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 December 17, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 December 19, ALS
- Nellie Nash to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1917 December 27, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 December 30, ALS
- Nellie Nash to Ella Katherine Fife 1917 [December], ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 January 2, ALS
- Shelton Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 January 12, Telegram
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 January 15, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 February 2, TLS
- [Shelton Stricker Fife] to Ella Katherine Fife ante [1918 February 5], AL
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 February 5, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 February 23, ALS
- Katherine Reynolds Fife to Margaret Whitler Fife [1918 February], ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 March 20, ALS
- Nellie Nash to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife ante [1918 March 20], ALS
- Nellie Nash to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 March 23, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 April 9, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 April 25, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 April 27, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 May 13, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 May 21, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 June 8, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, II to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 July 7, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 July 24, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 August 1, ALS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 August 1, ALS
- Hinda Strickler to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 August 6, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 August 7, ALS
- Katherine Mae Reynolds Fife to Margaret Whitler Fife ante [1918 August 10], ALS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife ante [1918 August 10], ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, II to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 August 10, TLS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 August 10, Envelope
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 August 11, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to James Douglas Fife 1918 August 17, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife [1918] August 18, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 August 21, ALS
- Mary Graves Fife Rinehart to James Douglas Fife 1918 August 24, ALS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 August 28, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 September 3, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 September 9, ALS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 September 12, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 September 14, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, II to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 September 18, TLS
- Nellie Nash to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 September 19, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife and A. E. Schultz to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 September 19, 20, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 September 22, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife [1918] September 23, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 September 26, ALS
- Ormond Strickler to Robert Herndon Fife, I and Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 September 26, APCS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to James Douglas Fife 1918 September 28, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 October 3, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, II to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 October 6, TLS
- Robert Herndon Fife, II to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 October 9, TLS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 October 11, ALS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 October 11, ALS
- Robert Herdon Fife II, to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 October 12, ALS
- Katherine Mae Reynolds Fife to James Douglas Fife 1918 October 13, ALS
- [Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife] to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 October [23], Envelope
- William Ormond Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 October 26, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 October 28, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 October 29, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 October 31, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 November 5, ALS
- Margaret Whitler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 November 7, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 November 10, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife and Robert Herndon Fife, I 1918 November 11, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 November 14, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 November 15, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Robert Herndon Fife, I 1918 November 18, Envelope
- Ella Katherine Fife to Robert Herndon Fife, I 1918 November 24, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Margaret Whitler Fife 1918 November 27, Envelope
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 November 28, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Margaret Whitler Fife 1918 November [28], ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 December 1, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to James Douglas Fife 1918 December 4, ALS
- Nellie Nash to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 December 5, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 December 11, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 December 12, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 December 14, TLS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 December 20, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 December 25, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 December 28, ALS
- Nellie Nash to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1918 December 29, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to James Douglas Fife 1918 December 30, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 December 30, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1918 December 31, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife [1918 December], Envelope
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1919 January 12, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Margaret Whitler Fife 1919 January 15, ALS
- Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife to James Douglas Fife 1919 January 17, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1919 January 19, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Margaret Whitler Fife 1919 January 30, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1919 February 6, ALS
- James Douglas Fife to Ella Katherine Fife 1919 February 8, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1919 February 14, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1919 February 17, ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Sarah Ann Graves Strickler Fife 1919 February 21, ALS
- Robert Herndon Fife, I to Ella Katherine Fife 1919 March 13, APCS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Robert Herndon Fife, I [1919], ALS
- Ella Katherine Fife to Mary Graves Fife Rinehart n. d., ALS
- G. L. Bartlett to Ella Katherine Fife n. d., ALS
- William Ormond Fife to Ella Katherine Fife n. d., ALS
- 3 picture postcards from Camp Lee n. d., ALS